hello and welcome everyone it's December
27 2022 we're in active bookstream
number
001.03
we're in the third in a series of
discussions on governing continuous
transformation
off to you blue
okay
so this book stream is going to be part
of an ongoing series of book streams at
the Active inference Institute so please
get in touch if you would like to
participate either in one of these dot
zero contextualization videos or an
upcoming discussion over the material
and these are all of our links here
this is a participatory online lab we
are open to interacting with anyone no
matter what your level of expertise is
in active in finance inference or
governance or other so the goal of this
bookstream is to discuss chapter three
we're going to go over the book map and
roadmap and the keywords of the chapter
and then there's two sections that kind
of fell out of this chapter three so
we'll split those up
um so we can just maybe introduce
ourselves so I'm blue Knight I'm an
independent research consultant in New
Mexico and I'll pass to Tyler
what's going I'm Tyler I'm more of a dow
practitioner out of California
I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and as this is our
year closing book stream and this is
going to be focusing on some board and
strategy related topics I think it'll be
interesting to talk about reflection and
how do we look back how do we Now cast
how do we look forward
nice yeah I'm definitely excited to
um align the material that is presented
in the book with um the ongoing
development of strategy and governance
in active inference Institute so that's
for me what I'm excited about today
Okay so this chapter is micro
foundations of strategic governance
and the two sections are the role of the
board and models of board cognition
um so Tyler do you want to read this
section of the abstract
sure right so there's no Universal
governance model the Strategic role of
the board does not does vary as a
function of cultural laws governance
orientation ownership structure and firm
context the period of 1998 to 2001 time
of financial markets rational exuberance
dominated by government governance
orientation centered around stock price
considerations has given birth to
today's compliance-driven governance
logic ruling public companies simply put
ever since corporate governance has been
estranging the board that's uniquely
integral part of strategy process
Chris Stanley during this very period
management research started
complementing their two demographic
input output models with behavioral and
cognitive Dimensions developing a new
conversation around the cognitive micro
Foundation support Effectiveness to this
day a study of the board strategic role
remains confined to the boardroom and
treats the environment as an exogenous
variable
we will take the next half
bye
oh
the top-down cultivated hierarchical
disconnect so characteristic of
traditional corporate governance and
strategy processes is more likely to
feel prediction error reinforcing the
perception that the world is
unpredictable and uncertain
indeed the very limitations of corporate
governance research may be an astute
reflection of the very real and often
self-inflicted limitations of the
board's strategic role shareholders are
challenged to ensure that the board's
full strategic potential is not wasted
more specifically there is a need for a
new self-organizing governance logic
okay
Tyler do you want to read this the role
of the board
yeah sure so for Section here is to roll
the board and then we'll go into really
different models of thinking about board
cognition
uh so we'll start this quote from Sean
there's no Universal governance model
the Strategic role of the board does
vary as a function of culture laws
governance orientation ownership
structure public private Equity founder
family-led controlled or combination
thereof in sperm-specific context
all right let's go to the next one
oh yeah this is upper echelon so um you
know not being familiar with like a lot
of business
um like vernacular I I just set this in
there so it's the high level of command
Authority or Rank and this can be like a
top level management or the board of
directors or both
um it seemed like that there was not
like it wasn't specifically defined in
the book as we're reading it but Tyler
do you have any like thoughts on that
specifically like what do you think
means how many times yeah my
understanding is that was a combination
of both the board and uh the top
management instructor
so yeah he left it pretty big but that's
my understanding
all right so we'll start off uh talking
about like what a board could be uh and
so this is bajan's definition of what a
board could mean and not necessarily
what it does mean so the board of
directors is a unique integral part of a
firm to Upper Echelon it asks from
within and without the firm as a
boundary spanner it should encapsulate
strategy processes to constructive
tension between organization and an
active environment exploit exploitation
and exploration as well as financial and
strategic controls
um and so I think even people outside of
like an active inference free energy
governance context would probably agree
with roughly this this definition that
like a board should be this Collective
governing body that used their
Collective wisdom uh because that the
idea is that is greater than just like
one person at the top making all the
decisions and that that Collective
wisdom something interesting and unique
comes out of that uh though that's not
necessarily what always happens
oftentimes it's not exactly what happens
so let's go to the the next slide we
talk about different uh so these are
different ways of thinking about how a
board like actually functions and
there's like a lot of different ways
like board the board the board's role
and like what they actually do an
organization varies considerably across
a lot of different dimensions
so one different way you could look at
it is uh the cultural uh background of
the board
so this is from a study I think if they
did this on Dutch Royal company which
had branches both in England and then
also in you know the rhyme in like
Germany right
and so they found that taught me they're
just having anglo-sax and corporate
governance orientation are more likely
to pursue exploitative and external
growth strategic renewal trajectories
while those having Orion corporate
governance orientation are more likely
to pursue exploratory internal growth
strategic renewal trajectories so I
think what they're implicitly saying is
that they're facing similar uh strategic
contexts they're the same company but
for some reason culturally they're more
oriented to doing certain kinds of
actions
then you can also think about it just by
the context of the business right there
might be certain boards that have
different roles that are more
appropriate for certain kinds of
contacts so some might be more
administrative maybe it's kind of like a
legal requirement to have the board and
that's kind of why they're there they're
more of just making sure that everything
is running on time more of an
entrepreneurial where they're actually
taking a more strategic role there's
directing and controlling we can imagine
that they're more uh kind of integrated
with management
and then their supervisor which might
just be hey making sure that everything
is is going okay that there are no uh
outrageous
um fraud that's being committed within
the company so a very common issue too
is that the board often doesn't have
much of a role at all uh and so this is
a quote from uh one of the studies at
The Shrine sites that managerial
hegemony Theory argues that boards are
legal fiction dominated by management so
the idea here is that management
actually runs the show you have a board
they have to check some boxes they're
often legally mandated right so like for
a
501c3 or a C Corp like you have to have
a board uh but they're like okay like
let's just appease regulators and and
have this board well not actually giving
them anything substantial to do
this is actually like a really big
problem in non-profit
um board management as well because it's
not it's very unclear what non-profit
boards are supposed to do and oftentimes
like non-profits will put a lot of
donors on their board in a lot of ways
just to appease you know these these
donors egos in exchange for getting more
more funded but without having a clear
sense of like what they're actually
supposed to do and this actually matters
quite a lot because if they don't know
what they're supposed to do but they
have all the power in the organization
like the board runs the organization in
a non-profit and so
they have like no accountability unclear
responsibilities but all the power and
so what that often dissolves into is
that the CEO or the executive director
is actually running the show and the
board is there just kind of like
checking boxes and
um more of a formality which does not
really get as a greater cognition that
the genre is hinting at it could be
possible uh by having a board so that's
unfortunate all right let's go to the
next one
all right
okay so
um this was the first of John's claims
there's a danger however that the
compliant board is breathing formalism
group think and risk aversion at the
expense of operational understandings
strategic focus and dependent thinking
effectively the board has been distanced
from initiating and directing strategic
renewal unless lawmakers of all
corporate governance guidelines in tune
with the requirements of a distributed
and discontinuous world the board is
either relegated to strategic relevance
or increasingly representative source of
inertia reflected by the struggle with
growing complexity
all right
um so let's just like unpack what jean
meant by irrational exuberance from that
claim
so irrational exuberance this is a a
famous quote from Alan Greenspan and
this was from the 1996 when this was
like the beginning of the.com Boom like
the.com boom still had a couple years
left to go before it really kind of
petered out uh they said irrational
exuberance is unduly escalated
asset values and so during this period
there's like the late 90s you got all
these companies that uh well one there's
like wild speculation in these companies
but also there wasn't great strategic or
financial controls by the by the boards
and so you had companies like Enron and
Tycho Worldcom that were like very much
misrepresenting their financials and so
the end result of this after the bus
the.com bust uh was the uh sarbanes
awfully I I always mispronounce this
sarbanes actually uh so
which in what that did was that it
created um the number of like audit and
Regulatory controls especially over the
board making sure the boards have
complex interests that they're actually
overseeing the organization effectively
which is all wonderful in many ways that
that can be great those are good things
but there's also a ton of Regulation
that imposes on these companies and it
also imposes a certain model of what a
board is supposed to be doing uh onto
these corporations and so John does not
like some aspects of that some of the
way that enforces wood board can and
should be
and so he says the 2002 sarbanes
obviously act the United States has been
the most prominent legislative
product resulting from irrational
exuberance composing Draconian measures
on the audit and financial
representations a publicly listed
companies
so
I think what a lot of what John is
saying about this period is that like
before 2002
um four-star games obviously you know
you had a lot of uh misrepresentations a
lot of rational exuberance but something
interesting that did happen during that
same period was that we also had a lot
of experimentation on what a board could
and should be and so you got a lot of
research during the same time thinking
about what managed your real cognition
what forward cognition actually looks
like what the boards of role could be
and that kind of free and lose culture
also created
um a more expansive view of what a board
is but then once you get into 2002 and
you get all these regulations from
starveying to honestly that really
constrained the idea of what a board
could be and put all of these other
burdens on top of the board and so it
really kind of diminished their
potential strategic and cognitive role
within the company
uh blue or Daniel do you have anything
you just want to add here
all right so that was talking about the
the rule of the board and that's all
just to say like the role of the board
is often extremely unclear like any like
non-profit or Corporation
um and so now it was on kind of switches
gears and says okay well let's think
about different models of board
cognition and different ways that you
can think about how a board could
operate
um so let's go to the next one
sure so rendova 1999 was among the first
to link managerial cognition
to corporate governance distilling the
board's distinct cognitive contribution
to strategy process specifically in
terms of environmental scanning and
interpretation her contribution can be
considered seminal laying grounds for a
stewardship-inspired corporate
governance approach that is now widely
adopted by Leading private Equity firms
where top management team and board
strategized together often in highly
complementary ways and based upon cash
financed equity-centric alignment of
interests as opposed to free call
options private Equity is more of a
governance than a financing model
explaining its Public Market equivalent
outperformance according to rendova
board directors do impact decisions
and so this I I thought that this idea
of managerial cognition
um was interesting it just like speaks
to my interest in hierarchical
um cognition at different levels so this
is the um a reference that uh gives that
is the managerial response to changing
environments perspectives on problem
sensing from social cognition so looking
at like what is managerial cognition so
this paper characterizes managerial
problem sensing and necessary
precondition for managerial activity
directed towards organizational
adaptation as composed of noticing
interpreting and incorporating stimuli
and I liked this like definition of
cognition really as like noticing
interpret interpreting and incorporating
stimuli although like in the paper they
don't say managerial cognition directly
I think that it's attributed largely to
this paper as very seminal in the field
um and then environmental scanning and
interpretation from the previous claim
also so that that this is the vendova
paper
um that Dijon cited and it says the
cognitive perspective in this paper
proposes
proposes suggests that directors
contribute to dealing with the
complexity and uncertainty associated
with strategic decisions it argues that
directors possess valuable
problem-solving expertise which they can
apply to a variety of contexts directors
make their cognitive contributions to
strategic decision making by performing
along with the firm's managers a set of
cognitive tasks scanning interpretation
and choice and like I noticed again this
like environmental scanning
interpretation and choice
does this like how does this relate to
like noticing interpreting and
incorporating stimuli like I think that
they're maybe you can it's like a
rephrase scanning interpretation and
choice
so
claim the Bichon makes in the paper he
says rendova appreciates the dynamic
nature of strategy process when she
postulates that board participation in
strategic decision making Rises with
increasing environmental complexity and
uncertainty however mendova's approach
is rather static as it falls short of
connecting the board table to the rest
of the organization and interchangeably
treats perception as interpretation
a free energy governance lens instantly
exposes the obvious shortcomings maybe
Tyler's gonna tell us how
[Music]
all right so let's go through a couple
more of these different models of
forward cognition one of them is called
stewardship Theory
um so to look quote here from one of the
original papers about stewardship Theory
Davis 2007 so economic approaches to
governance such as the agency theory
tend to assume some form of homo
economic use which depicts subordinates
as individualistic opportunistic and
self-serving alternatively sociological
and psychological approaches to
governance such as stewardship Theory
depicts subordinates as collectivists
grow organizational and trustworthy
um and so like there's I think a couple
different lenses you can think about
search Theory like one is kind of more
of this like communist version of a more
collectivist world where hey actually
we're not all fully selfish we actually
have more uh we also have like
collectivist aims and
um people it's like a different way of
thinking about like individual
motivation I think another one too is
that where this is really shine and
become
um actually important in like applied
practice it's been in private equity and
so in private Equity like the owners are
the same as the management and this
actually ends up mattering because what
they've seen these states have found
they can find this quote here is that
actually impacts
um
performance quite a bit
so
I think sorry we already read that quote
but the idea here is that when
management ownership are combined the
management acts as more stewards rather
than people who are just paper pushers
but they're actually really taking care
of this investment and more aligned with
the board interests
um okay the next one is absorbitive
capacity
so absorbit of capacity thinks about the
board as like a cognitive cognizing unit
that's informed by the experiences of
its members so some similar to what blue
said earlier uh that the board's
expertise the board's cognition isn't
foreign by the diverse experiences of
its board members so the ability of a
firm to recognize the value of new
external information assembly that and
apply it to commercial ends is critical
in its innovative capabilities we label
this capability from absorptive capacity
which suggests that it's largely a
function of the firm's level of Prior
related knowledge
uh it goes on to say it's from rendova
uh director's contribution as a source
of requisite varieties to increase the
pool of available interpretive
Frameworks on which decision uh group
in which the decision group can draw uh
so the idea here is that there's limited
information that any individual or any
group can can process you should get
more people so you could get more
diverse experiences so you could process
more information through different
models and that will lead to more
enhanced cognition
if I could add a note on that
previous slide
The Mention Of The requisite Variety in
the rendova quote is from cybernetics
and Ross Ashby's law of requisite
variety which is the idea that for a
system to be a good regulator adaptive
in a given environment that it needs to
have internal states that are of the
order of magnitude of external States
like if there's a hundred positions that
the food could be in but you're you can
only conceptualize of 10 then you're not
going to be able to have a granular or
nuanced enough perspective to like find
the food
so
um that ties the managerial and
strategic
practice oriented areas which frankly
dominate Society to some of the more
theoretical perspectives and system
independent perspectives on cybernetics
and cybernetic systems as cognitive
systems which is what brings this entire
discourse into the active inference area
yeah and I think that's also another
important lens on thinking about poor
diversity because a lot of times for
diversity is often seen through a more
of a political lens when there's also
like a computational lens as well that's
really important
foreign
contribution is relevant in three
regards first it is impossible to
meaningly infer board performance
from demographic variables in the
absence of a process model linking
demography and output second the board's
role as a group is essentially a
cognitive role and is therefore a
cognitive rather than behavioral
perspective is critical to better
understand the essence of board
performance and third effort Norms
cognitive conflicts and the use of
Knowledge and Skills are important
process variables underlying board
performance
Tyler's gonna tell us
effort norms and cognitive conflicts
all right so effort Norms I.E the
intensity of cognitive resourcefulness
on the task performance Behavior
cognitive conflicts the leveraging of
differences in perspective and the use
of Knowledge and Skills or important
process variables underlying poor
performance the dimension of effort
Norms cannot be stressed enough the
sheer presence of the collective pool of
competencies and experiences is rather
meaningless unless actively and
purposefully and exercised
so the idea here is that even if you
have a diverse set of perspectives on
your board even if you have like a
computational Firepower theoretically if
the board isn't absolutely inclined to
acting on that and processing that
information uh it's just not going to
happen in that that power you have that
potential power just doesn't really
matter uh I think this is important too
because a lot of boards see themselves
in a more passive in a more passive way
where like the CEO is feeding them
information and kind of giving them
things to rubber stamp approve and so
even if you have people who have that
those capabilities that capacity it's
not really even being used and so you
have to have a board that's actually
inclined to taking more of an active
role to really get that cognitive
potential
um from your board members
damn blue one thing out there yeah one
thought by analogy to the brain and the
central nervous system is like
the usage of resources for cognition and
the brain is still using a lot of energy
slightly less but a lot during sleep so
what exactly are these cognitive
conflicts what is the resource in the
case of the board is it the limited time
in a meeting where people can speak is
it limited attention to different
decisions is it
um what is it that's actually
um conflicted
and how do we gain insights from
thinking about the board as a cognitive
entity
so I think we'll we'll get some of those
soon when we talk about inertia
um but I think you're right in that like
the time the limited time constraints
are a huge factor of that where it's
just like you're less inclined to
actively do a very like high cognitive
task you know a very demanding cognitive
task if you have a couple hours every
month to really talk about it or in the
case of a 501c3 like board members are
unpaid and so if you're an unpaid member
there's probably like limited time
they're actually willing to put to
actually thinking about some of these
problems so I think that they're all a
lot of Dimensions to it but we'll talk
about that shortly
so so I think like this last end of this
quote um the competencies competencies
and experiences of the collective pool
is meaningless unless it's actively and
purposely exercised really speaks a lot
to collective intelligence
um and how like within a company aboard
a managerial system there is this this
collection and you're not um like
contributing to the the like emergence
of the group The Group intelligence if
um you're not using all of the different
uh expertises of of the different people
in the group and so I think that that
it's really limiting
um but but I also wonder
um you know like we might have a board
that's like a very diverse group of
people and we all have different tasks
in management different skills and
management but like we also can do
things like crochet and bake and like uh
paint and and so like to what extent are
these other skills that might be present
in the board like relevant or necessary
for like management to to thrive and
um like really to enhance the collective
for for the group I don't know
yeah one one last short thought on that
recalling the earlier quote how there's
no Universal governance model it's like
if we were talking about ant colony
strategies is it better to Simply have
more Nest mates or fewer or bigger brain
per body size or smaller it's like there
isn't a universal answer because there's
different strategies in fact multiple
strategies that might be adoptive in a
given Niche but it doesn't really make
sense to even talk about one without the
other whether you're talking about like
chess or ant colonies or the board and
so that's like where the particular
partitioning of active inference helps
because it reminds us that the cognitive
process of perception cognition
including action selection and then
action and action is happening within
the context of a generative process in
the niche and that can't be just like
left for later that's an intrinsic part
of the particular partitioning
okay so here Bhajan makes a claim that
essentially there are three important
conclusions to take forward from Golden
and zajac 2001 I don't know if I said
that right probably not uh first
demographic and procedural variables
impact strategic change rather curve
linearly second power relationships are
critical to understanding the impel
versus impede debate and strategic
renewal and third attentional focus and
engagement in terms of an okazolean
linkage of cognition and structure and
that's in this reference okay
Ocasio 1997 are a promising venue upon
which to pursue future research
um and then this linkage of cognition
and structure
um from this paper it's toward an
attention-based view of the firm
um from William Ocasio 1998. here he
says the central argument is that firm
behavior is the result of how firms
Channel and distribute the attention of
their decision makers what decision
makers do it depends on what issues and
answers they focus their attention on
what issues and answers they focus on
depends upon the specific situation and
on how the firm's rules resources and
relationships distribute various issues
answers and decision makers into
specific Communications and procedures
um and so that that like pushes salience
I think to the Forefront
um especially with regard to like you
know board collective intelligence like
maybe the crocheting and knitting and
baking and all those things are not
really relevant or maybe they could be
maybe this is the explore part where
active inference comes in
another another link here with attention
and structure and cognition is attention
to something that's more dynamic
but it requires the structural
connections like between brain regions
or at the synaptic level or uh apis that
call each other in a computational
system those pipes have to be in place
for attention to be dynamically
allocated and so the structural aspects
of the firm are more like it's
morphology and then the attentional and
the more rapidly changing aspects are
more like perception and fast changing
cognition and so that's going to be like
a theme that gets built upon are the
faster changing more perceptual and
decision making like components of the
firm and the slower changing more
structural elements of the firm
or just to build on that a little bit
like something I've noticed from prior
companies that even if you have a very
engaged board like a board that we they
would say gives a lot of attention
within the firm and has a high
intentional capacity like they may not
actually be linking that to the
structure of the firm so for example
something I've often observed is that
you'll have like two people putting to
go together the uh quarterly board deck
for a company of like a thousand people
right so everything gets processed
through this like tiny funnel of two
people who have to synthesize everything
on behalf of the board where they're
essentially just like making the
conclusions for the board at that point
and so if you're not really linking both
the attention and the structure you're
really missing out on like the potential
power of your board
all right uh inertia so inertia you
could think that really as just like
reluctance to change and similar to the
idea of like bounded rationality uh is
that there are certain constraints which
you have to reason that board often
reasons Within
so read a couple quotes from
um
I think it went off presentation mode
um so I'll read this quote from hand in
1977 he came up with the original idea
of inertia organizational inertia which
again isn't specific to uh the firms
it's really an idea that you can apply
to any Collective system so there are a
number of obvious limitations on the
ability of organizations to adapt that
is there are a number of processes that
generate structural inertia
and uh John says that indeed corporate
governance best practice skylines May
rather fuel governance inertia rather
than freeing the board as an impactful
supporting their impactful variable
supporting continuous strategic renewal
and so they make this like a little more
concrete and kind of go through a couple
different examples of inertia and these
all come from Hannah and second 77 paper
where he kind of defined this idea of
organizational inertia
so I'll list a couple of them one was
that previously made Investments aren't
easily transferable there are
constraints on the information decision
maker makers receive there are political
constraints there are closet history to
allocate tasks and create procedures so
like you've basically done all the work
to figure out who's doing what it's a
lot of work to like redo that there are
legal constraints perceptions of
legitimacy if you were to change course
at this point uh unclear how your
strategy will succeed in competitive
environments like if we do this how will
others react and so all of this just
creates a sense of like anxiety that
people just don't want to confront and
they feel good and comfortable uh
pursuing something that they already
understand and so you can think of that
as organizational inertia and this is
particularly a problem with boards
because especially if you have a board
with a limited attentional capacity like
they're not going to be putting the time
to really think they're going to work
through that anxiety they're not going
to be like actually doing the hard work
to overcome that and so you end up
having to defaulting to something that
people already understand and so there's
often something that you hear in
organizations where like okay well we we
could do this really ambitious thing and
like there are people who might be
actually excited about this more
exploratory initiative that you could do
but like how are we going to sell that
to the board
right and oftentimes it's the CEO has to
put their reputation on the line to sell
something that's more exploratory and
risky to the board who has limited
attentional capacity they're anxious
about it so they just kind of have to
trust this one person to say yes go for
it it's okay and so again you're not
really unlocking that uh that cognitive
power potential of the board
one one more aspect there on inertia to
connect to the Bayesian physics
inertia is something that physical
objects have in classical mechanics like
whether it's a a ball at rest that
requires some Force to push or whether
it's a bicycle and movement whose
inertia allows it to stay upright
inertia is an aspect of physical objects
and by analogy in the Bayesian physics
the inertia is like the resistance of a
prior to be updated to incoming
observations so a prior distribution
with a high inertia it's like a heavy
distribution it's immovable to new
stimuli and that corresponds to having
low attention because it's like as new
information comes in the prior has high
inertia it doesn't update a lot whereas
when there's High attention paid to the
incoming stimuli in the extreme the
prior just updates to whatever the new
stimuli says that's our new best
estimate so that's ultra high attention
and also very very movable
and that's um like a light object
and so there isn't a general answer but
this puts us into a framing where we can
think about this structural and
attentional inertia as part of the
morphological and dynamical cognitive
process of the board and the
organization more generally
yeah that I really like that perspective
on it and it makes me think about how
why position is spending so much time
thinking about the board because it's
kind of this combination of low
attention High responsibility uh for
updating like your the beliefs of the
organization and so that's where like a
lot of
just any like continuous change or
transformation would have to happen
start the board so I understand might be
trying to spending so much time thinking
about this and talking about different
models of board cognition
Hopman at Al 2019 make an invaluable
contribution in moving away from
deterministic models that suggest which
specific board configurations and
Leadership concentrations enhance board
Effectiveness firm performance and a
firm's overall strategic capability
instead they focus on the board's meta
capabilities such as self-evaluation and
self-reconfiguration to power continuous
strategic renewal
foreign
the board's power of vis-a-vis
management is strongly related to board
chair initiates self-evaluation and self
reconfiguration thereby ensuring that
the board can still critically evaluate
strategic proposals and reconfigure
strategies so unfortunately though hot
men at Al do not go far enough since
strategic renewal Remains bottlenecked
by the board chair we need governance
processes that neutralize the
overdependencies on the chairman and the
CEO so oftentimes within an organization
that has the board the chairman is kind
of running the show on the board and
their counter report is the CEO and they
do a lot of the agenda setting for how
the board actually operates how much
attention that they're actually giving
on to problems the kind of information
that's the incoming and available to the
board and so a lot of responsibility
relies on the board of like how
cognition can actually happen uh and
like I have been in this position myself
I've been a board chair a lot of
responsibility kind of ends up being on
you for how well the board and
consequently the organization can run
and so what's unfortunate and something
I've actually tried to do with myself is
like spread the responsibility of the
board chair uh throughout the board so
that cognition doesn't rust on like a
single person that's actually more
spread out through that entire you know
cognizing unit uh and that is difficult
to do so I'm curious if we've gone later
on in the book has uh some
recommendations on how to structure that
yeah I'm curious Tyler like what um you
know with respect to like the Dao world
that you live in like what are some
governance processes that do neutralize
that
um over over dependence on the chairman
and CEO of a company like what can you
you know maybe say a few words about
that
yeah so one I mean there's like a lot of
different governance processes but like
we kind of talk about a couple of them
so one is that like if you're doing
especially like token or token based
voting with the nfts or the rc20s like
any generally most people can make a
proposal not anyone can make a proposal
but like a lot of times the agenda
setting can be done in a distributed way
so it's not necessarily the board chair
and the CEO determining hey these are
the things that we're bringing up to a
vote but that can be done more
dynamically and oftentimes there's a
quorum like uh rules about who can
propose so it's not like fully
decentralized but in a sense like that
agenda setting can be done
more decentralized
um and there's also ways of creating
salience as well uh without having a
single person at the top saying what is
selling and what like what matters and
what doesn't there are ways there are
different governance strategies where
stallions kind of like bubbles up and
you can kind of determine
certainly governance rules like your
Quorum for example in a more like
Dynamic way
and so
there's a lot there how it can't work
then there's also like how it actually
works in practice and in reality like a
lot of times without governance like
usually often is like a couple people
making a lot of the proposals and so
what's interesting is that even if you
want to be in a more distributed way
like sometimes there's this like pull of
gravity towards centralized decision
making
and it really just is that there's like
limited attention available even if like
you're not saying you're not legally
mandating some kind of centralized
structure there's just like only a
couple people who are really willing to
like actually synthesize all this
information at any given time especially
within Dows like dab proposals are often
extremely Technical and there's often
limited people who can even like do that
if they wanted to
so like it's something that I've been
personally struggling with is thinking
about like okay well
there's this world that we want to live
in that's maybe more decentralized and
less hierarchical and more connected but
there's also just these constraints on
like human time and attention effort
capabilities that constrains the kind of
structures that you can have uh and
yeah and hopefully later in the book The
John will have some good recommendations
on how you can stress your organization
your board to kind of mitigate that like
pull towards centralized processes uh
but it's just something I've witnessed a
lot in like the DAT world as well
cool thanks
um so I think that that's the the end of
the material today so uh next week we
have the chapter is quite a bit longer
this one was pretty short
um but yeah we're looking forward I
think to um
what rajan's gonna tell us about free
energy governance and he's setting the
stage now for delineating the problems
and now like how do we go about solving
them I'm curious to delve into this next
section with you guys
can I bring up a few points and
questions
of course
all right so one of them was it
described the board as a spanner earlier
on and I wondered whether the board was
kind of like at the heart of the onion
insulated by more and more layers or
whether the board is on the front line
interfacing more publicly
in the actual position or that person
perhaps serving in a different position
as well like wearing multiple hats so
feel free to give any thoughts on that
or we can just raise the point
I mean my understanding of well there's
like how it actually works now and then
how it can work how it actually works
now is I think it's often more like in
the onion
uh where they are getting more refined
and more refined information that
filters through a hierarchy until it
finally gets to the board and what I
think the Jean is hoping for is
something that resembles more of like
like a motherboard like this integrating
unit where there's all these connections
from other parts of the organization
there's still that hierarchical
structure but is not insulated from the
rest of the organization and that I
think that's what the Drone is getting
at uh but from my understanding of board
governance like that is less often the
case and it's really hard to build
interesting
so I think that that's like a really
great question
um and I'd like to really kind of
explore it more in more detail when we
get into our discussion section so I
think we should add that to the dot one
um list
so
all right another topic is there was the
mention of a compliance
board as well as how a board could be
like dissonance or impel versus impede
and so how to
balance
between
uh simply going with what the body
provides
towards totally wishing things were
different it's like in the extreme
neither is going to work so there has to
be some middle path
but
there's no Universal model so that's
just kind of one point and then another
one was the market centrism of a
for-profit company
means that
in some sense but please suggest if
otherwise
the financial success on the broader
Market will Define the persistence and
the growth of the company
so that is kind of like projecting this
very high dimensional space of strategy
and composition and attention
projecting down onto a number line like
did the stock price go up or down
and so to what extent do
um for-profit and not-for-profit
organizations or components of
organizations
have clearer
or
more alignable
measures
because like I mean yeah it's just like
if the only Criterion of cognition was
this one test then you kind of get the
good Hearts law situation where other
measures can fall by the wayside so how
does that get prevented in or
ameliorated in for-profit Endeavors and
then on the other side how does that not
get ignored when there are very real
material constraints in non-profits as
well
yeah I forgot to mention this point
earlier but it's like a really important
one that like a lot of our model of like
shareholder governance is often very
like culturally specific to America so
there are other ways you could think
about uh board governance and corporate
governance so for example in uh
especially up in Germany there's like a
stakeholder governance model where for
example you're legally required to have
a board member in Germany who is a
representative of the workers
right and so this is more aligned with
like and you could think of that you
could expand that model too of like
stakeholder governance but that could
mean so that's just Germany's model
where they're like hey workers rights
need to also be important in addition to
profit right but you can also expand
that to think of okay well what if we
had an advocate for the consumer on the
board right like you could expand that
idea of what a for-profit company's
stakeholder governance model can look
like in Japan for example like there's a
lot of for-profit companies are also
like family run so there's these family
considerations on top of the for-profit
incentives as well so then between like
even like a between like a C Corp like
for-profit company and then a non-profit
there are different uh legal structures
that kind of bridge the distance between
the two so like one of the famous ones
is called a b Corp and so a b Corp it's
essentially the same thing as a C Corp
um it can make money it's a it's a
for-profit company but uh in the bylaws
they are not legally mandated to only
maximize for profit uh they can also
maximize for other they call it like
double bottom line initiatives so
they're like there's other things that
this for-profit company can try to do
aside from just
get money uh and then there's like a lot
of different permutations of that like a
lot of different legal structures you
can have that and same with a non-profit
too like even a non-profit couldn't have
ways that is trying to get Revenue uh
and think in a more for-profit way uh
even though there aren't people who are
shareholders who are going to profit
from it but they can they can act in a
similar way so I think often like the
the distinction between non-profit and
for-profit can actually become quite
fuzzy in the way that we think about
for-profit governance is often very like
culturally Centric on how we've done
things in the US and in England not
necessarily on like how it can be done
foreign
Daniel I think like what what I'm
curious to know like what goes into
defining or creating a compliant board
or like a dissonant board
um like I mean I would think that it's
like not structured to be a compliant
board I mean maybe they write it into
bylaws that the board just agrees with
everything that that everyone does but I
think it's more of like an emergent
property of the board and like does the
entire board need to be replaced if like
you say you have a compliant board and
you want more of like a strategy driven
governing board
like do you have to completely interrupt
like the the Norms right like we're you
know it like Bijan had said the Norms if
the norm is to be compliant like do you
have to just erase everyone to bring in
like a whole new crew to develop new
Norms otherwise like that one person
who's like oh let's just go along with
whatever everybody says like they'll
keep that culture alive right
um to clarify that I think what Bajan
meant was compliance board which is more
like if you're like in a regulatory if
you're a nuclear power plant for example
you want to have a compliance centered
board who's making sure that you're
following all the rules and regulations
but I think to your point blue like it
compliant board is also an important
like cloudboards function as compliant
boards are just rubber stamping
approvals and that is not super useful
so yeah I think that's also a good point
and one fun topic I think to do a little
research into is how did we even get
here with a board I mean isn't a board
or the table that was also mentioned
those are just like rectangles how did
we get to this point where the meeting
table
architecturally and the people gathered
around it have become legally required
and then even sub-constrained from there
and so really just thinking broadly as I
think in the
um Dao and other spaces people are
thinking broadly about what
organizational morphologies and what
developmental trajectories
and ecosystems of shared intelligence
facilitate
adaptive cognition
and what boards do and how they both
build on the Legacy and stay within that
lane of what may be legally required for
compliance as well as innovate and move
Beyond some of these um like
shortcomings and fallacies that boards
can fall into
yeah I've actually looked into this a
little bit about like how like why
boards are a thing and like for example
in non-profit boards like they were just
designed for like a different time when
a lot of times you were just getting
you're like basically foundations I had
a bunch of money that they were going to
allocate and they were like top-down
driven models not necessarily like
dynamically responding to to the world
around them and dynamically changing and
I think there's only a lot of four
profit corporations it was kind of a
similar idea is like we are going to
Charter this boat and we're gonna go to
this other country and we're gonna do
trade there and we're gonna like come
back right it was a more simple and like
linear model of thinking about planning
and so they're just made for a different
world and like I think NAB there's a lot
of legal infrastructure that has build
up around them so like actually
innovating around that's really
difficult so for example one thing I've
been working on a nonprofit recently
we're like well we don't want to have a
board we want to be more Community
Driven we want to be a co-op and so then
we we looked into being Co-op and
actually the legal infrastructure for
setting it up is actually just like not
developed at all you basically have to
have a lawyer spend thousands and
thousands of dollars to actually figure
out how that's going to work and it's
also very precarious even though like if
this thing is even going to work so it's
just really this well-trodden path has
just been beaten down over and over
again because it's the path of least
resistance but not necessarily the
optimal one for uh you know cognition
within the company
or announcement
I was going to say earlier like how did
we get here to this board right and it's
a script that like it's a script that is
has become solidified into law
um and it's the same thing like when you
have a compliant board like the rubber
Stampers
um and that's just also a script that
that they have followed so that's why
they're all compliant so and not really
kind of leveraging the type of
governance that would be maybe optimal
for the strategy of the company
okay cool cool yeah and the other final
final thoughts or we can hold it table
it for the upcoming discussion
rhythms of cognition rhythms of the year
the agenda setting the agenda
communicating with the board board
communicating with the organization
organization communicating outside the
organization
it's great topics and I think we're
um
three deep into the series
and we're just going to continue to see
how the scholarship and the legacy of a
lot of conventional and even heterodox
thinking and management is taking the
next step with this book and the
contribution that takes it into the free
energy governance space
cool
well thanks guys and we'll see you next
week for getting into the free energy
principle
all right thank you